<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc authorship="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<rfc  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" ipr='trust200902' tocInclude="true"  obsoletes="" updates="6550,8138" consensus="true" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" version="3" docName="draft-ietf-roll-turnon-rfc8138-02" >

<front>

   <title abbrev='Enabling RFC 8138'>Configuration option for RFC 8138</title>


   <author fullname='Pascal Thubert' initials='P.' role='editor' surname='Thubert'>
      <organization abbrev='Cisco Systems'>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
            <street>Building D</street>
            <street>45 Allee des Ormes - BP1200 </street>
            <city>MOUGINS - Sophia Antipolis</city>
            <code>06254</code>
            <country>FRANCE</country>
         </postal>
         <phone>+33 497 23 26 34</phone>
         <email>pthubert@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
   </author>

          <author initials='L' surname='Zhao' fullname='Li Zhao'>
          <organization abbrev='Cisco Systems'>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
          <address>
             <postal>
                <street>Xinsi Building</street>
                <street>No. 926 Yi Shan Rd </street>
                <city>SHANGHAI </city>
                <code>200233</code>
                <country>CHINA</country>
             </postal>
             <email>liz3@cisco.com</email>
          </address>
       </author>



   <date/>
   <area>Routing Area</area>
   <workgroup>ROLL</workgroup>
   <keyword>Draft</keyword>
   <abstract>
      <t>   This document complements RFC 8138 and dedicates a bit in the RPL
      configuration option defined in RFC 6550 to indicate whether RFC 8138
      compression is used within the RPL instance.
      </t>
   </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
   <section><name>Introduction</name>
      <t>  The transition to <xref target='RFC8138'/> in a network can only be
      done when all nodes support the specification. In a mixed case with both
      RFC8138-capable and non-capable nodes, the compression should be turned
      off.
      </t>
      <t>   This document complements RFC 8138 and dedicates a bit in the RPL
      configuration option to indicate whether RFC 8138 compression should be
      used within the RPL instance. When the bit is not set, source nodes that
      support RFC 8138 should refrain from using the compression unless the
      information is superseded by configuration.
      </t>
   </section><!-- title="Introduction"-->


<section anchor='bcp'><name>BCP 14</name>
<t>

    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
    "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
    <xref target='RFC2119'/><xref target='RFC8174'/> when, and only when, they
    appear in all capitals, as shown here.

</t>
</section>	<!-- end section "BCP 14" -->


   <section><name>Updating RFC 6550</name>
   <t>
   RPL defines a configuration option that is registered to
   IANA in section 20.14. of <xref target='RFC6550'/>. This specification
   defines a new flag "Enable RFC8138 Compression" (T) that is encoded in
   one of the reserved control bits in the option. The new flag is set to turn
   on the use of the compression of RPL artifacts with RFC 8138. The bit
   position of the "T" flag is indicated in <xref target='iana'/>.
   </t>
   <t>
   Section 6.3.1.
   of <xref target='RFC6550'/> defines a 3-bit Mode of Operation (MOP) in the
   DIO Base Object. The new "T" flag is defined only for MOP value between 0 to
   6. For a MOP value of 7 or above, the flag MAY indicate something different
   and MUST NOT be interpreted as "Enable RFC8138 Compression" unless the
   specification of the MOP indicates to do so.
   </t>
   </section><!-- Updating RFC 6550-->


   <section><name>Updating RFC 8138</name>

   <t>
   This document specifies controls that enable and disable the use of the
   <xref target='RFC8138'/> compression in a RPL Instance. Arguably, this could
   have been done in <xref target='RFC8138'/> itself.
   </t>

   <t>
   A node that supports this specification SHOULD source packets in the
   compressed form using <xref target='RFC8138'/> if the new "T" flag is set in
   the RPL configuration option from its parents. Failure to do so will result
   in larger packets, yields higher risks of loss and may cause a fragmentation.
   </t>

   <t>
   A node that supports this specification SHOULD refrain from sourcing
   packets in the compressed form using <xref target='RFC8138'/> if the "T" flag
   is reset. This behaviour can be overridden by a configuration of the
   node in order to cope with intermediate implementations of the root that
   support <xref target='RFC8138'/> but not this specification and cannot set
   the "T" flag.
   </t>

   <t>
   The decision of using RFC 8138 to compress a packet is made at the source
   depending on its capabilities and its knowledge of the state of the "T" flag.
   A router MUST forward the packet in the form that the source used, either
   compressed or uncompressed. A router that encapsulates a packet is the
   source of the resulting packet and the rules above apply to it in that case.
   </t>

   </section><!-- Updating RFC 8138 -->


   <section><name>Transition Scenarios</name>
   <t>
    A node that supports <xref target='RFC8138'/> but not this specification
    can only be used in an homogeneous network and an upgrade requires a
    "flag day" where all nodes are updated and then the network is rebooted
    with implicitely RFC 8138 compression turned on with the "T" flag set on.
   </t>

   <t>
    A node that supports this specification can work in a network with RFC 8138
    compression turned on or off with the "T" flag set accordingly and in a
    network in transition from off to on or on to off (see <xref target='mig'/>).
   </t>

   <t>
    A node that does not support <xref target='RFC8138'/> can interoperate with a
    node that supports this specification in a network with RFC 8138 compression
    turned off. But it cannot forward compressed packets and therefore it cannot
    act as a router in a network with RFC 8138 compression turned on. It may
    remain connected to that network as a leaf and generate uncompressed packets
    as long as imcoming packets are decapsulated by the parent and delivered in
    uncompressed form.
   </t>

   <t>
   <xref target='RFC6550'/> states that "Nodes other than the DODAG root MUST
   NOT modify this information when propagating the DODAG Configuration option".
   In other words, the configuration option is a way for the root to configure
   the LLN nodes but it cannot be used by a parent to advertise its capabilities
   down the DODAG. It results whether a parent supports RFC 8138 is not known
   by the child with the current level of specifications, and a child cannot
   favor a parent based on a particular support.
   </t>

   <t>Sections 8.5 and 9.2 of <xref target='RFC6550'/> also suggests that a
   RPL-aware node may attach to a DODAG as a leaf node only, e.g., when a
   node does not support the Mode of Operation
   of a RPL Instance, the Objective Function (OF) as indicated by the Objective
   Code Point (OCP) or some other parameters in the configuration option.
   But the node is also free to refrain from joining
   an Instance when a parameter is not suitable. This means that changing the
   OCP in a DODAG can be used to force nodes that do not support a particular
   feature to join as leaf only. This specification reiterates that a
   node that is configured to operate in an Instance but does not support a
   value for a known parameter that is mandatory for routing MUST NOT operate
   as a router but MAY still joins as a leaf. Note that a legacy node will not
   recognize when a reserved field is now used and will not turn to a leaf
   when that happens.
   </t>

   <t>
   The intent for this specification is to perform a migration once and for all
   without the need for a flag day. In particular it is not the intention to
   undo the setting of the "T" flag, and though it is possible to roll back
   (see <xref target='rb'/>), adding nodes that do not support
   <xref target='RFC8138'/> after a roll back may be problematic if the roll
   back is not fully complete (see caveats in <xref target='sic'/>).
   </t>

   <section anchor='mig'><name>Inconsistent State While Migrating</name>

   <t>
   When the "T" flag is turned on in the configuration option by the root, the
   information slowly percolates through the DODAG as the DIO gets propagated.
   Some nodes will see the flag and start sourcing packets in the compressed
   form while other nodes in the same instance are still not aware of it.
   Conversely, in non-storing mode, the root will start using RFC 8138 with a
   SRH-6LoRH that routes all the way to the last router or possibly to the leaf,
   if the leaf supports RFC 8138.
   </t>

   <t>
   This is why it is required that all the routers in the Instance support
   <xref target='RFC8138'/> at the time of the switch, and all nodes that do not
   support <xref target='RFC8138'/> only operate as leaves.
   </t>

   <t>
   Setting the "T" flag is ultimately the responsibility of the network
   administrator. In a case of upgrading a network to turn the compression on,
   the network SHOULD be operated with the "T" flag reset until all targeted
   nodes are upgraded to support this specification.  <xref target='sic'/>
   and <xref target='dic'/> provide possible transition scenarios where this can
   be enforced.
   </t>

   </section> <!--"Transient State while migrating"-->

   <section anchor='sic'><name>Single Instance Scenario</name>
   <t>
   In a single instance scenario, nodes that support RFC 8138 are configured
   with a new OCP, that may use the same OF operation or a variation of it. when
   it finally sets the "T" flag, the root also migrates to the new OCP. As a
   result, nodes that do not support RFC 8138 join as leaves and do not forward
   packets anymore. The leaves generate packets without compression. The parents
   - which supports RFC 8138 - may encapsulate the packets using RFC 8138 if
   needed. The other way around, the root encapsulates packets to the leaves all
   the way to the parent, which decapsulates and distribute the uncompresses
   inner packet to the leaf.
   </t>

   <t>
   This scenario presents a number of caveats:
   </t><ul spacing='normal'>
   <li>
   The method consumes an extra OCP. It also requires a means to signal the
   capabilities of the leaf, e.g., using <xref target='I-D.ietf-roll-mopex-cap'>
   "RPL Mode of Operation extension"</xref>.
   </li>
   <li>
   If an implementation does not move to a leaf mode when the OCP is changed to
   an unknown one, then the node may be stalled.
   </li>
   <li>
   If the only possible parents of a node are nodes that do not support RFC 8138,
   then that node will loose all its parent at the time of the migration and it
   will be stalled until a parent is deployed with the new capability.
   </li>
   <li>
   Nodes that only support RFC8138 for forwarding may not parse the RPI in
   native form. If such nodes are present, the parent needs to encapsulate with
   RFC8138.
   </li>
   </ul><t>
   </t>

   </section> <!--"Single Instance Scenario"-->

   <section anchor='dic'><name>Double Instance Scenario</name>
   <t>An alternate to the Single Instance Scenario is to deploy an additional
   Instance for the nodes that support <xref target='RFC8138'/>.
   The two instances operate as ships-in-the-night as specified in
   <xref target='RFC6550'/>.  The preexisting Instance that does not use
   <xref target='RFC8138'/>, whereas the new Instance does. This is signaled
   by the "T" flag which is only set in the configuration option in DIO messages
   in the new Instance.
   </t>

   <t>
   Nodes that support RFC 8138 participate to both Instances but favor the new
   Instance for the traffic that they source.
   On the other hand, nodes that only support the uncompressed format would
   either not be configured for the new instance, or would be configured to join
   it as leaves only.
   </t>

   <t>
   This method eliminates the risks of nodes being stalled that are described in
   <xref target='sic'/> but requires implementations to support at least two RPL
   Instances and demands management capabilities to introduce new Instances and
   deprecate old ones.
   </t>
   </section> <!-- Double Instance Scenario -->


   <section anchor='rb'><name>Rolling Back</name>

  <t>
   After downgrading a network to turn the <xref target='RFC8138'/> compression
   off, the administrator SHOULD make sure that all nodes have converged to the
   "T" flag reset before allowing nodes that do not support the compression in
   the network (see caveats in <xref target='sic'/>).
  </t>

   <t>
   It is RECOMMENDED to only deploy nodes that support <xref target='RFC8138'/>
   in a network where the compression is turned on. A node that does not support
   <xref target='RFC8138'/> MUST only be used as a leaf.
   </t>

   </section> <!-- Rolling Back -->

   </section> <!-- Transition Scenarios -->

   <section anchor="iana"><name>IANA Considerations</name>
    <t>
    This specification updates the Registry for the "DODAG Configuration Option
    Flags" that was created for <xref target='RFC6550'/> as follows:
    </t>

   <table  anchor="nexndopt"><name>New DODAG Configuration Option Flag</name>
   <thead>
      <tr><td>Bit Number</td><td>Capability Description</td><td>Reference</td></tr>
   </thead><tbody>
      <tr><td>2</td><td>Turn on RFC8138 Compression (T)</td><td>THIS RFC</td></tr>
   </tbody>
   </table>

   </section>

   <section anchor='sec'><name>Security Considerations</name>
    <t>
    Turning the "T" flag on before some routers are upgraded may cause a loss
    of packets. The new bit is protected as the rest of the configuration so
    this is just one of the many attacks that can happen if an attacker manages
    to inject a corrupted configuration.
    </t><t>
    Turning the "T" flag on and off may create inconsistencies in the network
    but as long as all nodes are upgraded to RFC 8138 support they will be able
    to forward both forms. The draft insists that the source is responsible
    for selecting whether the packet is compressed or not, and all routers must
    use the format that the source selected. So the result of an inconsistency
    is merely that both forms will be present in the network, at an additional
    cost of bandwidth for packets in the uncompressed form.
    </t>
   </section>

   <section><name>Acknowledgments</name>
   <t>
   </t>
   </section><!-- ack -->
</middle>

<back>

   <displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-roll-mopex-cap"        to="MOP-EXT"/>
   <references><name>Normative References</name>
	  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'/> <!-- BCP14 -->
	  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml'/> <!-- BCP14 -->
	  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6550.xml'/> <!-- RPL -->
   </references>
   <references><name>Informative References</name>
	  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8138.xml'/> <!-- 6LoRH for RPL artifacts -->
      <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-roll-mopex-cap.xml'/>
   </references>
</back>

</rfc>
