<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc authorship="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<rfc  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" ipr='trust200902' tocInclude="true"  obsoletes="" updates="6550,8138" consensus="true" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" version="3" docName="draft-ietf-roll-turnon-rfc8138-07">
<front>

   <title abbrev='Turn On 6LoRH'>A RPL Configuration Option for the 6LoWPAN Routing Header</title>


   <author fullname='Pascal Thubert' initials='P.' role='editor' surname='Thubert'>
      <organization abbrev='Cisco Systems'>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
            <street>Building D</street>
            <street>45 Allee des Ormes - BP1200 </street>
            <city>MOUGINS - Sophia Antipolis</city>
            <code>06254</code>
            <country>FRANCE</country>
         </postal>
         <phone>+33 497 23 26 34</phone>
         <email>pthubert@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
   </author>

          <author initials='L' surname='Zhao' fullname='Li Zhao'>
          <organization abbrev='Cisco Systems'>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
          <address>
             <postal>
                <street>Xinsi Building</street>
                <street>No. 926 Yi Shan Rd </street>
                <city>SHANGHAI </city>
                <code>200233</code>
                <country>CHINA</country>
             </postal>
             <email>liz3@cisco.com</email>
          </address>
       </author>



   <date/>
   <area>Routing Area</area>
   <workgroup>ROLL</workgroup>
   <keyword>Draft</keyword>
   <abstract>
      <t>
      This document updates RFC 8138 and RFC 6550 by defining
      a bit in the RPL configuration option to indicate whether RFC 8138
      compression is used within the RPL Instance, and specify the
      behavior of RFC 8138-capable nodes when the bit is set and reset.
      </t>
   </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
   <section><name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
      The transition of a RPL <xref target='RFC6550'/> network to activate the
      compression defined in <xref target='RFC8138'/> can only be done when all
      routers in the network support it.  Otherwise, a non-capable node acting as a router
      would drop the compressed packets and black-hole its subDAG. In a mixed
      case with both RFC8138-capable and non-capable nodes, the compression
      may be turned on only if all the non-capable nodes act as Hosts and
      their RPL parents handle the compression/decompression for them.
      </t>
      <t>
      This document complements <xref target='RFC8138'/> and dedicates a flag in the RPL
      configuration option to indicate whether <xref target='RFC8138'/> compression should be
      used within the RPL Instance. The setting of this new flag is controlled by the
      Root and propagates as is in the whole network. When the bit is not set,
      source nodes that support <xref target='RFC8138'/> should refrain from using the
      compression unless the information is superseded by configuration.
      </t>
      <t>
      With RPL, a leaf is an IPv6 Host, which implies that leaves do not forward packets.
      This specification provides scenarios that force a non-capable RPL-Aware Node
      (RAN) to become a leaf.
      The parent router must know, e.g., by configuration, or leveraging
      <xref target='I-D.ietf-roll-capabilities'>"RPL Capabilities"</xref>,
      when a leaf does not support the compression defined in
      <xref target='RFC8138'/>. This is implicitly the case for a RPL-Unaware
      Leaf (RUL) but is not known for a RPL-Aware Leaf (RAL). The parent router
      must uncompress the packets before delivering them to a non-capable leaf
      and it must compress the traffic from the leaf.
      </t>

   </section><!-- title="Introduction"-->


<section><name>Terminology</name>

<section anchor='lo'><name>References</name>
<t>
   The Terminology used in this document is consistent with and incorporates
   that described in <xref target='RFC7102'>"Terms Used in Routing for Low-Power
   and Lossy Networks (LLNs)"</xref>.
   Other terms in use in LLNs are found in <xref target='RFC7228'>
   "Terminology for Constrained-Node Networks"</xref>.
</t>



<t>"RPL", the "RPL Packet Information" (RPI), "RPL Instance" (indexed by a
   RPLInstanceID) are defined in <xref target='RFC6550'>"RPL: IPv6 Routing
   Protocol for Low-Power and Lossy Networks"</xref>. The RPI is the abstract
   information that RPL defines to be placed in data packets, e.g., as the RPL
   Option <xref target='RFC6553'/> within the IPv6 Hop-By-Hop Header.
   By extension the term "RPI" is often used to refer to the RPL Option itself.
   The DODAG Information Solicitation (DIS), Destination Advertisement Object
   (DAO) and DODAG Information Object (DIO) messages are also specified in
   <xref target='RFC6550'/>.
</t><t>

   This document uses the terms RPL-Unaware Leaf (RUL) and RPL Aware Leaf
   (RAL) consistently with <xref target='I-D.ietf-roll-useofrplinfo'>
   "Using RPI Option Type, Routing Header for Source Routes and IPv6-in-IPv6 encapsulation in the RPL Data Plane"</xref>.
   The term RPL-Aware Node (RAN) refers to a node that is either
   a RAL or a RPL Router. A RAN manages the reachability of its addresses and
   prefixes by injecting them in RPL by itself. In contrast, a RUL leverages
    <xref target='RFC8505'>"Registration Extensions for IPv6 over
    Low-Power Wireless Personal Area Network (6LoWPAN) Neighbor Discovery"
    </xref> to obtain reachability services from its parent router(s)
    as specified in <xref target='I-D.ietf-roll-unaware-leaves'>
    "Routing for RPL Leaves"</xref>.


</t>


</section>	<!-- end section "References" -->
<section anchor='gloss'><name>Glossary</name>
 <t> This document often uses the following acronyms:
    </t>
    <dl  spacing='compact'>
    <dt>6LoWPAN:</dt><dd>IPv6 over Low-Power Wireless Personal Area Network</dd>
    <dt>6LoRH:</dt><dd>6LoWPAN Routing Header</dd>
    <dt>DIO:</dt><dd> DODAG Information Object (a RPL message) </dd>
    <dt>DODAG:</dt><dd> Destination-Oriented Directed Acyclic Graph </dd>
    <dt>LLN:</dt><dd> Low-Power and Lossy Network </dd>
    <dt>RPL:</dt><dd> IPv6 Routing Protocol for Low-Power and Lossy Networks </dd>
    <dt>OF:</dt><dd> RPL Objective Function</dd>
    <dt>OCP:</dt><dd> RPL Objective Code Point</dd>
    <dt>MOP:</dt><dd> RPL Mode of Operation </dd>
    <dt>RPI:</dt><dd> RPL Packet Information </dd>
    <dt>RAL:</dt><dd> RPL-Aware Leaf </dd>
    <dt>RAN:</dt><dd> RPL-Aware Node  </dd>
    <dt>RUL:</dt><dd> RPL-Unaware Leaf</dd>
    <dt>SRH:</dt><dd>Source Routing Header</dd>


    </dl>
</section>	<!-- end section "Glossary" -->

<section anchor='bcp'><name>BCP 14</name>
<t>

    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
    "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
 <xref target='RFC2119'/><xref target='RFC8174'/> when, and only when, they
    appear in all capitals, as shown here.

</t>
</section>	<!-- end section "BCP 14" -->


</section>	<!-- end section "Terminology" -->


   <section><name>Updating RFC 6550</name>
   <t>
   This specification defines a new flag "Enable RFC8138 Compression" (T).
   The "T" flag is set to turn on the use of the compression of RPL artifacts
   with <xref target='RFC8138'/> within a RPL Instance. If a RPL Instance has
   multiple Roots then they must be coordinated to use the same setting.
   </t>
   <t>
   RPL defines a Configuration Option that is registered to IANA in section
   20.14. of <xref target='RFC6550'/>. The "T" flag is encoded in one of the
   reserved control bits in the RPL Configuration Option. The bit position of
   the "T" flag is indicated in <xref target='iana'/>.
   </t>

   <t>
   Section 6.3.1.
   of <xref target='RFC6550'/> defines a 3-bit Mode of Operation (MOP) in the
   DIO Base Object. The new "T" flag is defined only for MOP value between 0 to
   6. For a MOP value of 7 or above, the flag MAY indicate something different
   and MUST NOT be interpreted as "Enable RFC8138 Compression" unless the
   specification of the MOP indicates to do so.
   </t>
   </section><!-- Updating RFC 6550-->


   <section><name>Updating RFC 8138</name>



   <t>
   A node that supports this specification MUST source packets in the compressed
   form using <xref target='RFC8138'/> if and only if the "T" flag
   is set. This behaviour can be overridden by the configuration of the
   node in order to cope with intermediate implementations of the Root that
   support <xref target='RFC8138'/> but not this specification and cannot set
   the "T" flag.
   </t>

   <t>
   The decision of using <xref target='RFC8138'/> is made by the originator of
   the packet depending on its capabilities and its knowledge of the state of
   the "T" flag.
   A router that encapsulates a packet is the originator of the resulting packet
   and decides whether to compress the outer headers as indicated above.
   An external target <xref target='I-D.ietf-roll-useofrplinfo'/> is not
   expected to support <xref target='RFC8138'/>.
   An intermediate router MUST forward the packet in the form that the source
   used, either compressed or uncompressed, unless it is forwarding to an
   external target or delivering to a leaf that is not known to support
   <xref target='RFC8138'/>, in which cases it MUST uncompress the packet.
   </t>

   <!--t>
   A RUL <xref target='I-D.ietf-roll-unaware-leaves'/> is both a leaf and an
   external target . A RUL does not participate in RPL and
   depends on the parent router to obtain connectivity. Packets from/to a RUL are
   tunneled back and forth between the parent and to the Root regardless of the MOP used in the RPL Instance.
   </t-->


   </section><!-- Updating RFC 8138 -->


   <section><name>Transition Scenarios</name>
   <t>
    A node that supports <xref target='RFC8138'/> but not this specification
    can only be used in an homogeneous network. Enabling the
    <xref target='RFC8138'/> compression requires a "flag day"; all nodes must
    be upgraded, and then the network can be rebooted with the
    <xref target='RFC8138'/> compression turned on.
   </t>

   <t>
    A node that supports this specification can work in a network with <xref target='RFC8138'/>
    compression turned on or off with the "T" flag set accordingly and in a
    network in transition from off to on or on to off (see <xref target='mig'/>).
   </t>

   <t>
    A node that does not support <xref target='RFC8138'/> can interoperate with
    nodes that do in a network with <xref target='RFC8138'/> compression turned off. If the
    compression is turned on, the node cannot forward compressed packets and
    therefore it cannot act as a router. It may remain connected to that network
    as a leaf, generates uncompressed packets, and can receive
    packets if they are delivered by the parent router in the uncompressed form.
    Unless this is known by other means, the node SHOULD join as a RUL as an
    indication that its parent router needs to uncompress the packets before
    delivering.
   </t>

   <t>
   <xref target='RFC6550'/> states that "Nodes other than the DODAG Root MUST
   NOT modify this information when propagating the DODAG Configuration option".
   Therefore, even a legacy parent propagates the "T" flag as set by the Root
   whether it supports this specification or not. So when the "T" flag is set,
   it is transparently flooded to all the nodes in the RPL Instance.
   </t>

   <t>
   Sections 8.5 and 9.2 of <xref target='RFC6550'/> also suggests that a
   RAN may only attach to a DODAG as a leaf when it does
   not support the Mode of Operation of a RPL Instance, the Objective Function
   (OF) as indicated by the Objective Code Point (OCP) or some other parameters
   in the configuration option.
   </t>

   <t>
   This specification reiterates that a RAN that is configured to operate in a
   RPL Instance but does not support a value for a known parameter that is
   mandatory for routing, such as the OCP, MUST NOT operate as a router but MAY
   still join as a leaf. Note that a legacy RAN will not recognize when a
   reserved field is used and will not turn to a leaf when the "T" flag is set.
   </t>


   <t>
   The intent for this specification is to perform a migration once and for all
   without the need for a flag day. In particular it is not the intention to
   undo the setting of the "T" flag, and though it is possible to roll back
   (see <xref target='rb'/>), adding nodes that do not support
   <xref target='RFC8138'/> after a roll back may be problematic if the roll
   back is not fully complete (see caveats in <xref target='sic'/>).
   </t>

   <section anchor='mig'><name>Inconsistent State While Migrating</name>

   <t>
   When the "T" flag is turned on in the configuration option by the Root, the
   information slowly percolates through the DODAG as the DIO gets propagated.
   </t>

   <t>
   Some nodes will see the flag and start sourcing packets in the compressed
   form while other nodes in the same RPL Instance are still not aware of it.
   Conversely, in non-storing mode, the Root will start using
   <xref target='RFC8138'/> with a Source Routing Header 6LoRH (SRH-6LoRH)
   that routes all the way to the parent router or to the leaf.
   </t>

   <t>
   To ensure that a packet is forwarded across the RPL Instance in the form in
   which it was generated, it is required that all the routers support
   <xref target='RFC8138'/> at the time of the switch, and that all nodes that
   do not support <xref target='RFC8138'/> only operate as leaves.
   </t>

   <t>
   Setting the "T" flag is ultimately the responsibility of the network
   administrator. In a case of upgrading a network to turn the compression on,
   the network SHOULD be operated with the "T" flag reset until all targeted
   nodes are upgraded to support this specification.  <xref target='sic'/>
   and <xref target='dic'/> provide possible transition scenarios where this can
   be enforced.
   </t>

   </section> <!--"Transient State while migrating"-->

   <section anchor='sic'><name>Single RPL Instance Scenario</name>
   <t>
   In a Single RPL Instance Scenario, nodes that support <xref target='RFC8138'/> are configured with a new OCP, that may use the same OF operation or a variation of it,
   while nodes that do not support <xref target='RFC8138'/> are not, but are configured
   to join an unknown OCP.
  </t>

   <t>
   The Root migrates to the new OCP before it sets the "T" flag, so that nodes
   that do not support <xref target='RFC8138'/> are all attached as leaves when
   the "T" flag is eventually set.
  </t>

   <t>
   The parent router - which supports <xref target='RFC8138'/> - compresses the
   packets originated from the leaf and uncompresses the packets going to the
   leaf. This may be done on the fly by the parent of a non-capable RAL, or as
   part of the tunneling operation between the parent and the Root,
   if the leaf behaves as a RUL. This is described in section 7, 8, and 9 of
   <xref target='I-D.ietf-roll-useofrplinfo'/>.
  </t>

   <t>
   Note that though tunneling from the Root to the parent is the generic case
   for RULs, on paper it is possible for the Root to avoid it for the traffic
   that it originates. The Root SHOULD always use tunneling to the parent of a
   RUL, even for its own packets, unless it knows that the leaf supports
   <xref target='RFC8138'/>.
   </t>

   <t>
   This scenario presents a number of caveats:
   </t><ul spacing='normal'>
   <li>
   The method consumes an extra OCP. It also forces nodes that do not support
   <xref target='RFC8138'/> to operate as RULs, unless there is a method
   to let the parent router know that it must uncompress the packet for this
   RAL.
   </li>
   <li>
   If the RPL implementation of a node does not turn it to a leaf when the OCP is changed to
   an unknown one, then the node may be stalled.
   </li>
   <li>
   If the only possible parents of a node are nodes that do not support <xref target='RFC8138'/>,
   then that node will loose all its parent at the time of the migration and it
   will be stalled until a parent is deployed with the new capability.
   </li>
   </ul>


   </section> <!--"Single Instance Scenario"-->

   <section anchor='dic'><name>Double RPL Instances Scenario</name>
   <t>An alternative to the Single RPL Instance Scenario is to deploy an additional
   RPL Instance for the nodes that support <xref target='RFC8138'/>.

   </t>

   <t>
   The two RPL Instances operate independently as specified
   in <xref target='RFC6550'/>.  The preexisting RPL Instance does not use
   <xref target='RFC8138'/>, whereas the new RPL Instance does. This is signaled
   by the "T" flag which is only set in the configuration option in DIO messages
   in the new RPL Instance.
   </t>

   <t>
   Nodes that support <xref target='RFC8138'/> participate in both Instances but
   favor the new RPL Instance for the traffic that they source.
   By contrast, nodes that only support the uncompressed format would
   either not be configured for the new RPL Instance, or would be configured to
   join it as leaves only.
   </t>

   <t>
   This method eliminates the risks of nodes being stalled that are described in
   <xref target='sic'/> but requires implementations to support at least two RPL
   Instances and demands management capabilities to introduce new RPL Instances
   and deprecate old ones.
   </t>

   <t>
   The 2 instances MUST be operated with the same security guarantees, e.g.,
   both "unsecured" with a lower layer security of a same strength, both
   "preinstalled" or both "authenticated" security mode (see section 3.2.3 of
   <xref target='RFC6550'/> for more details on those modes). The latter mode
   could be use to enforce the segregation of updated and non-updated nodes, by
   providing the keys for joining as routers to the updated nodes only.
   </t>


   </section> <!-- Double Instance Scenario -->


   <section anchor='rb'><name>Rolling Back</name>

  <t>
   After downgrading a network to turn the <xref target='RFC8138'/> compression
   off, the administrator SHOULD make sure that all nodes have converged to the
   "T" flag reset before allowing nodes that do not support the compression in
   the network (see caveats in <xref target='sic'/>).
  </t>

   <t>
   It is RECOMMENDED to only deploy nodes that support <xref target='RFC8138'/>
   in a network where the compression is turned on. A node that does not support
   <xref target='RFC8138'/> MUST only be used as a leaf.
   </t>

   </section> <!-- Rolling Back -->

   </section> <!-- Transition Scenarios -->

   <section anchor="iana"><name>IANA Considerations</name>
    <t>
    This specification updates the Registry for the "DODAG Configuration Option
    Flags" that was created for <xref target='RFC6550'/> as follows:
    </t>

   <table  anchor="nexndopt"><name>New DODAG Configuration Option Flag</name>
   <thead>
      <tr><td>Bit Number</td><td>Capability Description</td><td>Reference</td></tr>
   </thead><tbody>
      <tr><td>2</td><td>Turn on RFC8138 Compression (T)</td><td>THIS RFC</td></tr>
   </tbody>
   </table>

   </section>

   <section anchor='sec'><name>Security Considerations</name>
    <t>
   First of all, it is worth noting that with <xref target='RFC6550'/>, every
   node in the LLN that is RPL-aware can inject any RPL-based attack in the
   network. A trust model MUST be put in place so that rogue nodes are excluded
   from participating to the RPL and the 6LowpAN signaling, and from the data
   packet exchange.  This trust model could be at a minimum based on a Layer-2
   Secure joining and the Link-Layer security. This is a generic RPL and 6LoWPAN
   requirement, see Req5.1 in Appendix of <xref target='RFC8505'/>.
 </t>
    <t>
    Setting the "T" flag before some routers are upgraded may cause a loss
    of packets. The new bit is protected as the rest of the configuration so
    this is just one of the many attacks that can happen if an attacker manages
    to inject a corrupted configuration.
    </t><t>
    Setting and resetting the "T" flag may create inconsistencies in the network
    but as long as all nodes are upgraded to <xref target='RFC8138'/> support they will be able
    to forward both forms. The source is responsible
    for selecting whether the packet is compressed or not, and all routers must
    use the format that the source selected. So the result of an inconsistency
    is merely that both forms will be present in the network, at an additional
    cost of bandwidth for packets in the uncompressed form.
    </t>
   </section>

   <section><name>Acknowledgments</name>
   <t>The authors wish to thank Dominique Barthel and Rahul Jadhav for their in-depth reviews and constructive suggestions.
   </t>
   </section><!-- ack -->
</middle>

<back>

   <displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-roll-useofrplinfo"     to="USEofRPLinfo"/>
   <displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-roll-unaware-leaves"     to="UNAWARE-LEAVES"/>
   <displayreference   target="I-D.ietf-roll-capabilities"        to="CAPABILITIES"/>
   <references><name>Normative References</name>
	  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'/> <!-- BCP14 -->
	  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml'/> <!-- BCP14 -->
	  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6550.xml'/> <!-- RPL -->
  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7102.xml'/> <!-- RPI -->
 	  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7228.xml'/> <!-- RPI -->
      <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-roll-useofrplinfo.xml'/>
      <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-roll-unaware-leaves.xml'/>
   </references>
   <references><name>Informative References</name>
   	  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6553.xml'/> <!-- RPI -->

	  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8138.xml'/> <!-- 6LoRH for RPL artifacts -->
  	  <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8505.xml'/> <!--6LoWPAN ND -->
     <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-roll-capabilities.xml'/>
   </references>
</back>

</rfc>
